Guide to the N. Scott Momaday Papers
Beinecke Rare Book and Manuscript Library
- Papers, 1788-2012; 1950s-2012
  - Copies of photographs of Kiowa members from the A.A. Hyde Collection of Williams S. Soule Photographs from Wichita State University Special Collections, undated (Box 10)
  - Information on the Native American Cultural Center Inc. with lists of committee members, plans for the new cultural center, By-Laws, and collections management plans., undated (Box 10)
  - Booklets and announcements of awards and recognition of NSM: Oklahoma Annual Governor's Arts Award, 1999 (2 copies); Oklahoma Today Special Edition of the 50 most important Oklahomans with NSM on pg. 28 (2 copies); Arts Oklahoma, Fall 1999 with NSM on the front page, Clippings of the newspaper article on the 50 most influential Oklahomans, circa 1990s (Box 10)
  - Correspondence with the State of Oklahoma Supreme Court regarding presentations and support of The Buffalo Trust, undated (Box 10)
  - Oklahoma Museum of History about NSM donation to the museum, Copy of Oklahoma Today pinned with an invitation to Robert Henry's birthday and one of his poems, undated (Box 10)
  - Speaking Engagement Offer to speak at Southeastern Oklahoma State University November 14, 2003, circa 2000s (Box 10)
  - Spiral bound copy of A History of Riverside Indian School Anadarko, Oklahoma 1871-1971with an invitation to the 1999 graduation celebration of Julia Rose Noel and other pieces of information on the school, circa 1990s (Box 10)
  - Wood framed photograph of a woman with a reindeer, undated (Box 11)
  - Piece of woven cloth, undated (Box 11)
  - Correspondence with Professor Stefano Varese regarding the possibility of NSM working at University of California, Davis 1993, circa 1990s (Box 11)
  - Print of a drawing by Al Momaday on a mat, and newspaper clipping from the 1970s about Al Momaday, circa 1970s (Box 11)
  - College of Santa Fe 33rd Annual Commencement program listing NSM to give the graduate address, May 9 1982, circa 1980s (Box 11)
  - "Cases and Materials on Torts" by Charles O. Gregory and Harry Kalven, Jr. copyright 1956, bound together with handwritten notes in the margins throughout the entire document, circa 1950s (Box 11)
  - Green plastic binder with materials from presentations NSM gave in France. Most material is in French., undated (Box 11)
  - Hard bound recorders book with handwritten names and addresses from 1956-1958. Looks like a guest book, but no information is provided, circa 1950s (Box 11)
  - Book: The Junior Instructor Book 2 Signed to Natachee S. Momaday on the inside cover with an itinerary of Stonehenge traditions inside, undated (Box 11)
  - "Cases and Materials on Torts" by Charles O. Gregory and Harry Kalven, Jr. copyright 1956, bound together with handwritten notes in the margins throughout the entire document, circa 1950s (Box 11)
  - "Cases and Materials on Torts" by Charles O. Gregory and Harry Kalven, Jr. copyright 1956, bound together with handwritten notes in the margins throughout the entire document, circa 1950s (Box 11)
  - Binder labeled "Case Briefs" with NSM name in it and his address is Charlottesville, VA, undated (Box 11)
  - Spiral notebook with NSM name on the cover with notes from 1957under a tab labeled "Property", circa 1950s (Box 11)
  - Tax information including forms, receipts, bank statements, and income information for NSM 2002, circa 2000s (Box 11)
  - Doctor's business cards and a pharmacy slip; Photo of Al Gore signed to NSM with a note from the office of the vice president; Letter to Mrs. Clinton from NSM dated April 30, 1999; Email from Marna Madsen about an opening on the National Council for the Humanities asking NSM to join, May 6, 1998; Invitation for NSM to visit the white house at the request of Hilary Clinton; Bio of NSM, 1999; Questionnaire for National Security Positions; Paper work for members of the Designated Agency Ethics Officials, 1993., circa 1990s (Box 11)
  - Legal correspondence and paperwork concerning a car accident in Louisiana on May 29, 1997 which NSM was passage in a cab that was hit, circa 1990s (Box 11)
  - NSM Individual Income Tax Returns December 31, 2000 portfolio by Sisneros, Norris & Duffy, P.C. Certified Public Accountants, circa 2000s (Box 11)
  - American Express Card statements, 1998; Paperwork and correspondence regarding a Russian visa fro NSM for a conference and a time he would be in Russia, 1998; passport photo; information about the conference and NSM trip to Russia, circa 1990s (Box 11)
  - Correspondence between NSM and Anne D. Goodman, Esq. regarding the publication and publicity for Circle of Wonder, 1998; Correspondence with Clear Light Publishers regarding publishing agreements for Circle of Wonder and payments; Contact between NSM and Clear Light Publishers for Circle of Wonder 1993-1998, circa 1990s (Box 11)
  - Statements for C.N.A. homeowners insurance 1998; New York Life Insurance statements, 1999; Principal Financial Group Statements, 2001; California Casualty Personal Auto Policy statements, 1998; Perfection Auto Craft of Santa Fe statements, 1998, circa 1990s (Box 11)
  - United States Department of the Interior Office of the Special Trustee for American Indians Trust Funds Management letter and statements, 1998, circa 1990s (Box 11)
  - NSM account information with the Teachers Insurance and Annuity Association College Retirement Equities Fund, 1992-1995, circa 1990s (Box 11)
  - "Hunters of the Dawn: Unnu Land" by Laure Morali, April 2001 with a not on the cover to NSM; Email about plays NSM sent to Annamaria Pinazzi; French contract (in French); Agreement between NSM and Editions Du Rocher regarding The Names; Letter from Daniele Laruelle, 1998, circa 2000s (Box 11)
  - Royalty Statements and contract agreements from HarperCollins Publishers for House Made of Dawn 1998-2001, circa 1990s (Box 11)
  - Program for a conference on Edward S. Curtis in France at which NSM presented a paper "The Spirit Drawn with Light: Edward Curtis and the American Indian" December, 2000; French newspaper (2001) with a story on NSM on page 25; Photocopies of France media coverage of NSM (2001); Imprevu magazine, July/Aug 2001 with a story on NSM on page 46, circa 2000s (Box 11)
  - Letter from the Department of the Treasury about a tax refund, June 18, 1996, circa 1990s (Box 11)
  - Legal order to terminate child support for Lore Claire Scott Momaday since she has turned 18, June 26 1998; Letter from Regina-Heitzer Momaday to NSM with attached medical insurance information for Lore Momaday, 1998; Decree of Dissolution of Marriage of the marriage of Regina Heitzer-Momaday and NSM, March 21, 1995; Notes for NSM trust and Will; Separation of property agreement., circa 1990s (Box 11)
  - Lore's budget 1998-1999; Delta Airline tickets for Lore roundtrip Tucson to Tenn., July 1999; Day-Timer statement, 1999; handwritten notes on expenses, circa 1990s (Box 11)
  - Correspondence with French presses, particularly Editions du Rocher regarding the publication of "The Ancient Child" and The Way to Rainy Mountain and House Made of Dawn 1993 all in French, circa 1990s (Box 11)
  - Business cards, mostly from France; Confirmation of NSM engagement at the Adler Planetarium and Astronomy Museum, July 30, 2000, circa 2000s (Box 11)
  - Correspondence with Futures for Children, 2002; Letter from Pioneer Library System; Letter regarding the Arizona Book Festival, 2004; Letter to Frances McCue, Sherman Alexie, and Lois Welch at Hugo House regarding and invitation to an event, 2004; Correspondence with the Santa Fe Board Members, 2004; numerous requests from varying parties requesting NSM to speak or appear at events in 2004, circa 2000s (Box 12)
  - Handwritten notes and budgets; Citibank Advantage 1998 Annual Account Summary; American Express Platinum Card Year End Summary 1998; Receipts for Airline travel, The Plaza in NYC, Avis, meals; American West Airlines Receipt; Airline ticket stubs, restaurant and misc. receipts from 1998; Hotel receipt from Adams Mark in Tulsa, circa 1990s (Box 12)
  - Handwritten notes and budgets for Business expenses; Royalty statements from 1998 and tax income forms for 1998; Tax forms, circa 1990s (Box 12)
  - Receipts: from postal service, library; Sioux Trading Post, the Candy Man, Artisan Santa Fe, Fed Ex, Desert Son of Santa Fe, Frame of Mind, Self Storage, etc. from 1998, circa 1990s (Box 12)
  - Mortgage Interest Statements, 1998, Tax Bill; homeowners insurance 1998, circa 1990s (Box 12)
  - Handwritten notes on income and budgets, Simon and Schuster statement; Houghton Mifflin Company royalty statements St. Martin's Press royalty statements; Glencoe/McGraw-Hill statements; W.K. Kellogg Foundation Statement; Axium Statement; University of Arizona Statement; Other Royalties and Earning statements all from 1998, circa 1990s (Box 12)
  - Checkbook stubs from NSM checkbook, 1998, circa 1990s (Box 12)
  - Banking statements from Wells Fargo Bank; Jemez Valley Credit Union statements; First State Bank Statements; 1997-1998 calendar pages; 1998 Middlebury College calendar; 1998 spiral calendar, circa 1990s (Box 12)
  - Walgreens Pharmacy receipts and prescription information Equipment rental for crutches, 8/24/98; University physicians statement; Family foot care receipts; Foundation Health National Life explanation of benefits, circa 1990s (Box 12)
  - Electricity bills and statements, phone and internet bills; Cell phone bills; and other household bills from 1998, circa 1990s (Box 12)
  - Handwritten budgets and notes; Statements from Daniel J. Hochuli & Associates, P.C. Attorneys at Law, undated (Box 12)
  - Letter from Tom Costello regarding tax returns; handwritten figures of 1099 tax information; 1996 taxes prepared by Sisneros, Norris & Duffy, P.C. Certified Public accountants, circa 1990s (Box 12)
  - Handwritten budgets and tax figures for 1997; Statements and receipts including royalty payment statements all dating to 1997, circa 1990s (Box 12)
  - Handwritten list of expenses; Year-end Summary for the American Express Platinum Card; Von Holtzbrinck Publishing Services royalty statement; FedEx receipts; Misc. receipts for expenses such as office supplies,; invoice for computer equipment for 1997, circa 1990s (Box 12)
  - Handwritten budgets; Airline ticket stubs and receipts; restaurant receipts, Hotel receipts; Travel expense reports; Rental car receipts, circa 1990s (Box 12)
  - Handwritten list of medical expenses; Pharmacy receipts; donation receipts, circa 1990s (Box 12)
  - Handwritten list of expenses; Phone and internet bills from US West Communications; Housekeeping invoices; Auto loan statements; Electric bill statements; Auto maintenance bills; Water and sewer bills; Self-Storage bills; Rent check singed by NSM (not cashed); other misc. statements related to household expenses for 1997, circa 1990s (Box 12)
  - Kentucky Ancestors: Quarterly of the Kentucky Historical Society Winter 1987 Vol. 22 Num. 3, circa 1980s (Box 12)
  - 1975 Standard Daily Journal with hand written address and journal entries. It is hard to determine if this is NSM or his wife's journal, circa 1970s (Box 12)
  - Spiral bound copy of Navajo Stories by Natachee S. Momaday, 1967, circa 1960s (Box 12)
  - Photographs of Natachee S. Momaday dating to the 1960s. These are posed shots of her with her book, helping children at school and in her office; photo of the Day school open house arts expo circa 1960s; postcard of Via Coeli Monastery; Contact prints of Natachee's portraits; photograph of NSM as a child in Shiprock in 1936; photograph of Juan Gachupin; Photo of Mrs. Joe Tosa, Mrs. Christina Panana; photograph of U.C.L.A. Workshop on Human Relations Pacific Area, Los Angeles. Taken in July 1956 in front of one of the sorority houses. Small photographs of Natachee on a wagon, 1947, Beehive oven, Mrs. Joe R Toya cleaning wheat, Holy Infant Shrine, Back yard of Natachee's school, first home and birthplace, old photo of Jerez Pueblo (Box 12)
  - Correspondence regarding the Heinz Awards; NSM letter of support for W. Richard West., undated (Box 12)
  - Memorial papers for Natachee S. Momaday, September 26 1996 by NSM, multiple copies, circa 1990s (Box 12)
  - Letter correspondence to Natachee S. Momaday dating to the 1960s; Biography of Natachee, circa 1960s (Box 12)
  - Dried flowers from Natachee Mementos, undated (Box 12)
  - Award to Natachee S. Momaday in a blue presentation book Electing Natachee to the New Mexico Folklore Roll of Honor; Spiral bound notebook with a few notes inside, undated (Box 12)
  - Newspaper clipping of an article on the rights of the mentally ill, 1978; Newspaper clipping on a fire destroying a house in Kentucky, 1978; sympathy cards to NSM about the death of Natachee; Art gallery opening announcements; Names and addresses on notebook paper; Cards to Natachee from NSM and other family members, circa 1970s (Box 12)
  - Postcards from the Navajo reservation from mid-1960s, Newspaper clippings: "Long March Parade Here" in Albuquerque Journal, July 3 1968; 3000 See Navajos Re-Enact signing of Sumner Treaty July 1, 1968; clippings from 1968 marked with a note that reads "Background for ideas for Novel" in Natachee's handwriting; Two giant postcards from the Navajo Reservation c. 1960s, circa 1960s (Box 12)
  - Handwritten "Descriptions" of Grandmother's Hogan, undated (Box 12)
  - Page from a book with photographs labeled "Meeting of the tribal council" and "Washing Clothes where water is scare"; :A Three-Forked-Pole Hogan", "A modern type Hogan"; "An earth-covered Hogan", A Shade giving shelter for outdoor cooking"; Article from the Ute Bulletin about Arrow Inc. Aids Indians, Sept. 1964 and a description assignment, undated (Box 12)
  - Travel and Leisure Magazine November 1975; Newspaper clippings of news from Albuquerque in 1967 mostly reporting weather and snow; A "Description" by Natachee, and a "Merry Christmas" note from Northwestern regional library staff., circa 1970s (Box 12)
  - Dust jacket to Owl in the Cedar Tree; Brochures for places in New Mexico; prayer cards and bookmarks; University of New Mexico Baccalaureate Service 1958, circa 1950s (Box 12)
  - Handwritten notes (NSM notes?) some dated 1954, circa 1950s (Box 12)
  - A Guide to Navajo Rugs, 1992, circa 1990s (Box 13)
  - "The Stanford Magazine" 1975, "Welcome Kiowa Gourd Clan Ceremonials, July 1, 2, 3, 4" 1976; "American Indian Exposition" 1969, circa 1970s (Box 13)
  - Kiowa Indian Calendar; Southwest Indian Arts and Crafts; "Where magazine" 1980 with a story on the Momaday family on page 5; "About Town" guide with the Momadays featured on page 10; "New Mexico" magazine, 1970 with an article on Al Momaday by Dorothy Dunn on page 36, circa 1980s (Box 13)
  - University of Arizona Department of English Annual Performance Review on NSM, 2003; NSM Annual report, 2003; NSM Annual report, 2000; NSM performance review 2002; NSM Annual report 2001; NSM Bio, circa 2000s (Box 13)
  - Honorary degree from the University of New Mexico to NSM, 2001 with the commencement program, circa 2000s (Box 13)
  - Letter from Jackie Autry regarding a planning meeting for the Stewardship Council of the Autry National Center; pamphlet on NSM The Indolent Boys adopted for radio; Correspondence with the Autry Museum regarding the collaboration between the museum and the Buffalo Trust on oral history of the Kiowa, 2003; NSM employment papers; The Indolent Boys for radio, circa 2000s (Box 13)
  - University of New Mexico Yearbook "Mirage" 1955 with NSM on page 126, circa 1950s (Box 13)
  - University of New Mexico Yearbook "Mirage" 1958 with NSM on page 53, circa 1950s (Box 13)
  - University of Arizona Department of English Course descriptions Fall 2002; Department directory 2002-2003; class rosters and grade lists 2003; Notes to his research assistant, circa 2000s (Box 13)
  - Information from the Student Achievement Advocacy Services asking NSM to speak about his life at the Adventures of the Mind event the organization hosted on Nov. 5 2002, circa 2000s (Box 13)
  - Information on Konza Prairie and buffalo, undated (Box 13)
  - Memorabilia and photographs from an Arizona rafting tour that NSM went on, 1999, circa 1990s (Box 13)
  - Correspondence and agreements between NSM and Donald M. Skirvin regarding setting some of NSM poems to music, 2000, circa 2000s (Box 13)
  - Border book festival papers and contracts for a reading by NSM at the festival, 2003, circa 2000s (Box 13)
  - Writing, appears to be a speech, undated (Box 13)
  - Contracts, itineraries and information packet for a presentation NSM made at Lawrence University, 2003, circa 2000s (Box 13)
  - Contracts, itineraries and information packet for a presentation NSM made at Brown University, for the Native American History Series, March 2003 plus media coverage in newspapers, circa 2000s (Box 13)
  - Correspondence between Joran Mjoberg in Sweden and NSM, 1999, circa 1990s (Box 13)
  - 92nd Streety: Tisch Center for the Arts, Unterberg Poetry Center. January 2003 with an announcement of NSM reading along side Simon Ortiz on Jan. 6th (3 copies), circa 2000s (Box 13)
  - University of Alaska Fairbanks letter informing NSM that he has been named a UAF Northern Momentum Teacher/Scholar for the fall semester of 2001-02, circa 2000s (Box 13)
  - Various correspondence including letters from Harry Wilmer and the Institute for the Humanities at Salado, 2000; Patricia Juskowitz, 2000; "Alex"; Picture and class listing on the St. Mary High School Class of 1951, circa 2000s (Box 13)
  - Information on NSM support of the Jemez Springs Library including clippings from events he attended there, 2003, circa 2000s (Box 13)
  - Program for the Historic Barter Theatre, 2000 with "Children of the Sun" listed as one of the performances that season; Menu for the Dancing Crow Café in Glade Springs Virginia; Newspaper clipping about the Dancing Crow; Robert Porterfield Memorial book; Posters and announcements for performances of "Children of the Sun", circa 2000s (Box 13)
  - University of Arizona payroll and personnel information forms and performance reviews, undated (Box 13)
  - University of Arizona notice of reappointment, class cover forms, and travel expense report form, undated (Box 13)
  - NSM resume, 1994 and the AZ State Library Association Newsletter Nov. 1993, circa 1990s (Box 13)
  - Letters and resumes from students asking for recommendations of for NSM to serve on their dissertation committees, undated (Box 13)
  - NSM Biography, undated (Box 13)
  - Notice of reappointment; personnel forms; biography and resume; annual reports and listing of English faculty at University of Arizona, undated (Box 13)
  - Magazines: Etonnants Voyageurs Telerama, June 4 2001;Hors-serie Geo Indiens d'Amerique du Nord, circa 2000s (Box 13)
  - Photographs from NSM trip to Siberia?, undated (Box 13)
  - 8x10 b/w photographs of family with negatives and a receipt for the photos dated 1/5/76, circa 1970s (Box 13)
  - Historic Barter Theatre playbills for Children of the Sun, 2000 (8 copies), circa 2000s (Box 13)
  - Unmarked negative strips in an envelope. Appears to be from the 1972, circa 1970s (Box 13)
  - Envelope of letters from the 1930s Letters to Mr. Clark; Research?, circa 1930s (Box 13)
  - Clippings of articles by NSM in "Viva" a Santa Fe newspapers from 1972, circa 1970s (Box 14)
  - Various untitled type writings by NSM while he was at University of California, Santa Barbara, undated (Box 14)
  - Draft writings: "Tuckerman and The Cricket" and "The Way to Rainy Mountain" with handwritten edits, undated (Box 14)
  - Various newspaper clippings on Natachee, Al and NSM 1970-80s, circa 1970s (Box 14)
  - Booklet of San Francisco Street Names by the American Trust 1951; University of New Mexico 83 Commencement 1975 W/ NSM listed as giving the commencement address, circa 1970s (Box 14)
  - Manuscript of "Bend with the Reed by Natachee S. Momaday with publishing correspondence, undated (Box 14)
  - Spiral notebook labeled "Papers to be graded and filed", undated (Box 14)
  - Natachee's tax form from 1968; poster for NSM exhibition of art work at the Gallery of the 21st Century, 1980, circa 1960s (Box 14)
  - Spiral bound booklet "Weavings" 1979, circa 1970s (Box 14)
  - Kiowa Guard Clan Ceremonials 1976 booklet; 8x10 b/w photos of Natachee with a note that they are for her book, 1976, circa 1970s (Box 14)
  - Barrister 1957; the yearbook of the University of Virginia Law School, circa 1950s (Box 14)
  - Letters in French, Poem "A Tree's Supplication" with no author; Program for the Book and Author Luncheon at the Santa Fe Hilton Inn May 16, 1975; Piece of lace (collar to a dress?); Photo of the Pope, circa 1970s (Box 14)
  - Drawing and handwritten poem (Untitled) by NSM, undated (Box 14)
  - First Draft of The Names by NSM, undated (Box 14)
  - Black and white photographs of the House Made of Dawn Movie Shoot, undated (Box 14)
  - Correspondence between Natachee S. Momaday and publishing companies, undated (Box 14)
  - Natachee's resume, undated (Box 14)
  - Manuscript of Owl in the Cedar Tree by Natachee S. Momaday; Memoirs by Natachee, undated (Box 14)
  - Bottom to a calendar and a letter to Natachee from the members of Theta State, The Delta Kappa Gamma Society about "Owl in the Cedar Tree", undated (Box 14)
  - Photographs of NSM in a book, undated (Box 14)
  - Various postcards; A guide to Haworth Parish Church; guidebook to Avila Spain; Guide book to Avignon; guidebook to Pueblo of Jemez; Guidebook to the Osterley Park House, undated (Box 14)
  - Greeting cards with a print of Al Momaday's artwork on the cover, undated (Box 14)
  - Yearbook 1970 Anadarko Area; Bureau of Indian Affairs with NSM on the cover, circa 1970s (Box 14)
  - Personal letters to and from Natachee and Al Momaday, c. 1970s, circa 1970s (Box 14)
  - Al Momaday business card; Al Momaday mailing labels; Art card with a work by Al Momaday; Blurb on NSM in The American Poetry Review; Booklet reprint from the World of the American Indian by National Geographic Society with "I Am Alive…" by NSM, undated (Box 14)
  - Newspaper clippings of stories on the Momaday family c. 1960-1970s, circa 1960s (Box 14)
  - Big Hogan by Natachee S. Momaday, 1968, circa 1960s (Box 14)
  - Natachee's Wrangler Award by the National Cowboy Hall of Fame and Western Heritage Center; Correspondence between Natachee and Northland Press about book fairs and Owl in the Cedar Tree, 1976; Leather invitations to the 16th Annual banquet of the National Cowboy Hall of Fame and Western Heritage Center, circa 1970s (Box 14)
  - "Betty A Navajo Girl", "Navajo Stories" and "Turquoise" by Natachee S. Momaday, undated (Box 14)
  - "A Visit to Grandmother" (2 copies), "Lucky Lobo", and "Navajo Reader No. 5" by Natachee S. Momaday, undated (Box 14)
  - List of books in print as part of NSM research, 1996, circa 1990s (Box 14)
  - Information and correspondence regarding a trip to Siberia along with NSM written story of how he came to be involved in the trip., 1997, circa 1990s (Box 14)
  - "The Story of Tsoai" by NSM, undated (Box 14)
  - Photocopy of pages 178-185 of House Made of Dawn; Photocopy of The Ancient Child, Correspondence with St. Martin's Press, undated (Box 14)
  - "The Ordeal of Plenty Horses" by Robert Utley; "Sweetgrass" a play by NSM (drafts), undated (Box 14)
  - Drafts of "The Indolent Boys" by NSM, undated (Box 14)
  - Aboriginal Voices Magazine April/May/June 1997 with an article "Revisiting Sacred Ground" by NSM; Dust jacket to "House Made of Dawn"; The Kennedy Center and National Symphony Orchestra Professional Development for Teachers Performances for school groups 1996-97 and travel information, circa 1990s (Box 14)
  - Governor's Awards for Excellence in the Arts program with NSM as a recipient for literature, 1996, circa 1990s (Box 14)